[Music]
recall that the binomial coefficient n
choose a represents the number of ways
of selecting a unordered objects from a
set of size n
consider the lattice of points in the
plane with non-negative integer
coordinates let's label the origin and
the point a b
how many northeast lattice paths are
there from 0 0 to a b where a northeast
path is one that only allows steps
directly right or up
let's enumerate them for a equals 2 and
b equals 3.
as we build all the paths we realize
that each path has the same number of
steps namely a plus b
moreover we see that each path has
exactly a steps to the right and b steps
up
so we only need to keep track of where
and when the right steps occur
[Music]
we can keep track of these steps by
listing off the order of the steps
for instance
the first path is r r u u u because the
right steps happen first and the last
path is u u u r r because the two right
steps happen at the end
a consequence of this encoding is that
the north east lattice paths to av
correspond to strings of r's and u's
with ars and bu's
thus such a lattice path corresponds to
a selection of a unordered positions
from a plus b spots to place the rs and
the u's go in the other spots
hence northeast lattice paths to a b are
counted by the binomial coefficient a
plus b choose a
returning to our lattice paths
we see that we can group them by their
final step
so in our example
four end with a right step and six end
with an up step
notice that all the paths ending in r
must first pass through the point a
minus one comma b
[Music]
similarly all the paths ending in an up
step u must first pass through the point
a comma b minus one
[Music]
these two collections of paths are
clearly disjoint and make up all of the
possible northeast lattice paths to the
point a b
thus
a plus b choose a
is equal to a minus 1 plus b choose a
minus 1 which is the number of lattice
paths to a minus 1 comma b
plus
the binomial coefficient a plus b minus
1 choose a which is the number of
lattice paths to a comma b minus 1.
replacing a plus b by n
results in n choose a equals n minus 1
choose a minus 1 plus n minus 1 choose a
this is the binomial recurrence
[Music]
you